<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: agile | ædʒirei]]></title>
  <link href="http://pzol.agirei.com/blog/categories/agile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pzol.agirei.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-07T20:57:03+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://pzol.agirei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Piotr Zolnierek]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experience vs Attitude]]></title>
    <link href="http://pzol.agirei.com/blog/2011/02/14/experience-vs-attitude/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-14T14:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pzol.agirei.com/blog/2011/02/14/experience-vs-attitude</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When interviewing new people for a job as an agile developer, what qualities should you be looking for?
Is it sufficient to check the previous experience and the knowledge in the areas he will be needing for your projects or is the attitude more important?</p>

<h3>Attitude</h3>

<p>A developer is like an engineer, always looking for improvement, always trying out new things and trying to make his work more productive,
at the same time he is proud of his work and makes sure it works properly. What has made him act this way is his attitude.</p>

<p>Then you have programmers, which simply translate instructions into code.</p>

<p>I like the word developer, as it derives from development, according to the dictionary, to develop means <em>to grow or cause to grow and become more mature, advanced, or elaborate</em>.
Hence a developer is somebody who <strong>causes some application to grow and become more advanced</strong>. A programmer just translates ideas into code. This is not enough.</p>

<p>According to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attitude_(psychology">wikipedia</a>, attitude is</p>

<blockquote><p>An attitude is a hypothetical construct that represents an individual's degree of like or dislike for something.</p></blockquote>

<p>Another view of what attitude is comes from buddhism, there we have the <a href="http://www.thebigview.com/buddhism/eightfoldpath.html">Eightfold Path</a>,
which is the way to end suffering, i.e. achieve Nirvana.
In terms of software to reach Nirvana, is to end all suffering coming from maintaining legacy project.</p>

<p>An excerpt says:</p>

<blockquote><p>Right effort can be seen as a prerequisite for the other principles of the path.
Without effort, which is in itself an act of will, nothing can be achieved,
whereas misguided effort distracts the mind from its task,
and confusion will be the consequence.
Mental energy is the force behind right effort; it can occur in either wholesome or unwholesome states.</p></blockquote>

<p>For me in our context this means, that somebody needs to <strong>be determined to do the right thing</strong>
and that attitude or the right effort is the prerequisite to become a great developer.</p>

<p>In real life a developer needs to behave accordingly in all kind of daily situations.
As our team becomes more cross-functional, not only in terms of specialization on programming languages or special areas of expertise within the area of coding,
a developer needs to have the right <strong>likes</strong> of the following areas:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Quality - A developer needs to have the right attitude to automate deployment, so that every time her work is put into production it works flawlessly.
Quality means predictability, that said, a developer needs to work on a proper test suite, making sure what was working once, doesn't get broken accidentally.</p></li>
<li><p>Customer Value - what we build must be valuable for the customer, developer must avoid creating waste and
<strong>communicate</strong> with the customer directly to make sure to have the same common understanding of value.</p></li>
<li><p>Continuous Learning - a developer must always learn new things, in his technology, programming language and also in other areas like databases, operating systems etc.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Experience</h3>

<p>Then on the other hand there is experience, which is the sum of a person has learned, of all mistakes he did, of everything good or bad,
that happened in his life.</p>

<p>If you are building a new team or a new project where you have no expertise yet, you might want to lay more emphasis on experience and hire people,
which have already done what you are trying to accomplish.</p>

<p>We all learn by trial and error, especially software engineers need to see for themselves what is working and what is not.
Then on the other hand, we cannot allow to make mistakes which jeopardize our customers business.</p>

<p>In order to move forward safely, you have to have people which have made a reasonable amount of errors so they won't do them on your new mission-critical project.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>In my opinion the art (as in martial art) of software development requires people to be truly cross-functional
- in their abilities to learn, to take on tasks which are not necessarily their favorite
and to continuously <em>steal</em> knowledge from other areas in order to keep improving.
Thus, the conclusion for me is straightforward, the right effort or in other words the right attitude, is crucial, specific skill can be acquired along the path.</p>

<p>So in the end, the right answer is - it depends. If you are looking for a long-term investment, and already have a basis,
you might lay less importance on experience and more on the right attitude.</p>

<p>If you do not have a solid foundation in the form of experienced people, you really need to build that first.
You can build good software with unexperienced people, it will take longer and will cost you more,
but with people with a bad attitude you will most probably build bad software, which will be hard to maintain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
